On June 22nd, 1986, in front of 114,000 screaming fans at the Azteca Stadium, one man did the impossible.
He grabbed the ball in his own half — and ran. Past one defender. Then another. Then another.
Sixty yards, ten seconds, five defenders and a goalkeeper — all left behind.
Four minutes earlier, that same man had cheated. He punched the ball into the net with his fist and got away with it.
His name was Diego Armando Maradona.
And this is the story of how the greatest footballer who ever lived destroyed himself.
Villa Fiorito. A shantytown on the edge of Buenos Aires, where the streets had no names and the houses had no floors.
This is where Diego was born on October 30th, 1960.
His father worked in a factory. His mother raised eight children in a house smaller than most people's living rooms.
Diego got his first football at age three. And from the moment he touched it, everyone knew something was different.
By eight years old, he was performing halftime tricks at professional matches.
His youth team won 136 consecutive games. Without a single loss.
At fourteen, he signed with Argentinos Juniors. At fifteen, training with grown men twice his size.
On October 20th, 1976, Diego Armando Maradona made his professional debut.
He was the youngest player to ever set foot on an Argentine professional pitch.
But talent born in poverty comes with a price.
The boy who had nothing suddenly had everything. And no one taught him how to carry it.
By twenty-one, Maradona had scored 115 goals for Argentinos Juniors.
Boca Juniors bought him, and he won the Argentine league in his first season.
In 1982, FC Barcelona paid five million pounds — a world record — for a twenty-one-year-old from the slums.
But Barcelona was a disaster. Hepatitis struck first.
Then Goikoetxea shattered his ankle with a tackle so vicious it nearly ended his career.
Thirty-eight goals in fifty-eight games — incredible numbers for a broken man.
Then came Naples.
On July 5th, 1984, Maradona arrived at Stadio San Paolo by helicopter. 75,000 fans were waiting.
They chanted: Ho visto Maradona — I have seen Maradona.
Naples was the poorest city in Italy. But Maradona gave them something they never had: pride.
He won Napoli their first-ever Serie A title in 1987. Then another in 1990.
He didn't just play for Naples — he became their god.
They call him D10S — Dios, the Spanish word for God, fused with the number 10.
The 1986 World Cup in Mexico. This is where Diego Maradona became immortal.
Argentina had been knocked out early in 1982. The country was reeling from the Falklands War.
When the two nations met in the quarter-finals, it wasn't just football. It was war by other means.
The score was zero-zero at halftime.
Then, in the fifty-first minute, the ball deflected into the air off England's Steve Hodge.
Maradona and Shilton both jumped. Shilton was taller. But Maradona's fist got there first.
He punched the ball into the net. The referee didn't see it.
A little with the head of Maradona, and a little with the hand of God.
But what happened four minutes later made the world forget the cheating.
Maradona receives the ball in his own half. He turns. And he runs.
Past Beardsley. Past Reid. Fenwick lunges — nothing but air.
Butcher closes in. Maradona goes around him. Butcher tries again. Around him a second time.
Just him and Shilton. The goalkeeper spreads wide. Maradona drags the ball past him into an empty net.
Sixty yards. Ten seconds. The greatest goal ever scored.
In the final, 2-2 with six minutes to go. Maradona threaded the pass. Burruchaga scored the winner.
Argentina were world champions.
Five goals, five assists — ten of Argentina's fourteen goals.
Ninety dribbles. Fouled fifty-three times. The Golden Ball by unanimous vote.
The single greatest individual performance in the history of team sports.
The god had a demon. And the demon's name was cocaine.
In Naples, the parties never stopped. The Camorra surrounded him.
The women. The drugs. The lifestyle of a living deity.
On March 17th, 1991, cocaine in his system. Fifteen months banned.
The city that worshipped him watched him leave in disgrace.
He went to Sevilla. Then back to Argentina. The drugs never stopped.
In 1994, he returned to the World Cup. Thirty-three. Overweight. Out of shape.
Against Greece, he scored and ran to the camera, screaming with bulging eyes.
It was terrifying. It was electric. The last great moment of his career.
Four days later, positive for five variants of ephedrine. Expelled.
His World Cup was over. His career at the highest level was over.
No one believed him.
After retirement, the man who could do anything with a football could do nothing without one.
His weight ballooned to 280 pounds. In 2000, a cocaine-induced heart attack.
In 2004, another. In 2005, gastric bypass surgery.
He tried coaching. Argentina — eliminated by Germany four-nil.
His final post was at Gimnasia. He was still their coach when it happened.
November 25th, 2020. Cardiac arrest in his sleep. He was sixty years old.
Hundreds of thousands lined the streets of Buenos Aires, in a global pandemic, to say goodbye.
His heart weighed nearly twice the normal size.
Eight members of his medical staff are standing trial for negligent homicide.
Diego Maradona was born with nothing in a shantytown with no name.
He became the greatest footballer the world has ever seen.
He was worshipped as a god. And he destroyed himself with the same hands that once touched the divine.
He was not a perfect man. But he played perfect football.
And for those who saw him — truly saw him — nothing else ever came close.